[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-three]
[第三十三集]
I propose
我提议
The meeting broke up after a while.
一会儿散会了
Take each branch factory as a unit.
以各分厂为单位
Everyone is going to take to the streets to support students.
组织大家准备上街声援学生
And go to the presidential palace to petition, okay?
并且到总统府去请愿 好吧
good
好
middle
仲澥
The physical condition of the arrested students
被捕学生的身体状况
And mental condition?
和精神状况怎么样
Most of the students' mood is relatively stable.
[邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
Have done a comprehensive and reactionary government.
已经做好了全面与反动政府
Long-term preparation for Zhou Xuan
长期周旋的准备
Just because the police arrested him violently.
只不过因为警察暴力逮捕
Many students were injured.
许多同学受了伤
Plus no food, no water.
再加上没有食品 没有水
And no medicine.
也没有药品
So many people are sick.
所以很多人生病了
This is a hurdle.
这是个坎儿啊
I'm going to check on them later.
回头我要去看看他们
Sir, you can't go
先生 您不能去
We've found out before.
之前我们已经发现
The police informant gave you to the town.
警察的线人把您给盯上了
It's too dangerous for you to come forward now
您现在出面实在太危险了
be
是
Liu Yipin followed me when I came.
我来的时候刘一品就跟在我后面
It's too dangerous for you to go.
您去太危险了
I'm fine
我没事
Just take care of Mr. Zhongfu.
你们照顾好仲甫先生就行
You are equally important to us.
您对我们同样重要
None of you can do without the student movement.
学生运动少了你们哪一位都不行
I won't let you go
我不会让您去的
That way.
那这样
That's all I have on me. Take it.
我身上就带这么多了 你拿着
Shiyan goes back at night
世炎 晚上回去
You come with me to get some money
你跟我去拿点钱
Take this money to the students.
拿这些钱给学生们
Buy some medicine and food.
买点药品 食物
Take care of them.
照顾好他们
good
好
At the same time, I also hope that everyone
同时 我也希望大家
Can mobilize the surrounding forces.
能够发动一下周围的力量
Money, money, strong efforts.
有钱的出钱 有力的出力
Will you help the students through this difficulty?
帮助学生们渡过这道难关 好吗
good
好
The vast number of workers and friends
广大的工人朋友们
This is the most dangerous moment right now.
眼下是最危难的时刻
Who gritted his teeth until the end?
谁咬牙坚持到最后
Who can win the final victory?
谁就能取得最后的胜利
Everyone heard it just now.
刚才大家也都听见了
We arrested more than 1000 students.
我们被捕了一千多名学生
heavy loss
损失惨重
But just because
但是正因为
More than 1000 students were arrested.
这一千多名学生被捕了
Let all the Chinese people see it.
让全中国的人民都看到了
Reactions of Beiyang government
北洋政府的反动
At the critical moment when the country was betrayed
在国家被出卖的关键时刻
These students stepped forward.
这些学生挺身而出
At the expense of personal interests and future.
不惜牺牲个人利益和前途
Weigh with the blood of youth.
用青春的热血抨击了
Shake with the heat of youth.
政府的卖国行径和反动本质
And with their patriotic feats.
也用他们的爱国壮举
Awaken all the people.
把所有的人民都给唤醒了
I firmly believe that as long as we hold on a little longer
我坚信 只要我们再坚持一下
The situation will definitely change.
形势一定会有变化
Of course, in the process
当然 在这个过程当中
Everyone should also take care of themselves.
大家也要照顾好自己
You can't be rash or make unnecessary sacrifices.
不能莽撞 不能做无谓的牺牲
Beware of reactionaries jumping into a wall.
要谨防反动派狗急跳墙
Although it is such a dark time.
虽然眼下是这么一个黑暗的时期
I still believe
我依然相信
As long as we unite and work hard
只要我们团结一致 努力奋斗
The final victory must belong to us.
最后的胜利一定属于我们
Unite to win.
团结一致 夺取胜利
Director Wu
吴总监
All the students arrested yesterday were put in the temple of horses.
昨天抓的学生都关到了马神庙
But now the temple of horses along the North River
但是现在北河沿 马神庙
Are surrounded by ordinary people.
都被老百姓给围住了
You can't stop anyone who asks for food.
要求送吃的 拦都拦不住
this is great
这太好了
People have helped us a lot.
老百姓帮了咱们大忙了
The students have food.
学生们有吃的了
Notify Duan Zhigui
通知段芝贵
Put the north river along the horse temple
把北河沿 马神庙的
Open all doors, big and small.
大大小小的门都给我打开
Allow ordinary people to deliver food.
允许老百姓来送吃的
Jiaozi steamed bun noodles can do anything.
包子 饺子 面条什么都可以
You can also send clothes
送衣服也行
Not Director Wu.
不是 吴总监
That's not a free market.
那 那不成自由市场了
Shut up and go for it.
闭嘴 赶快去力
be
是
Old guys, are you standing still?
老几位 你们愣着干什么
Come to a meeting.
来 开会 开会
Yi qunxian
易群先
He Mengxiong
何孟雄
Kuaiqiu
快瞅
Mrs. Chen
陈师母 师母
Eat while it's hot
趁热吃
There you are.
你们在这儿呢
You can come.
你们可来了
Locked up here.
被关到这儿了
I've been worried sick. I haven't heard from you.
我担心死了 没你们的消息啊
Are you all right?
你们都没事吧
never mind
没事 没事
Are you hungry?
饿坏了吧
famished
饿死了
Come on, come on.
来 来 快
Come and eat steamed stuffed bun, students.
来 快吃包子 同学们
come
来
very delicious
真好吃
Qun lai xian he Zhou
群先 来喝粥
There's food, there's food.
还有吃的 还有吃的啊
Delicious!
好好吃啊
Liu Mei
柳眉
There's food here.
这儿 这儿还有吃的
Give it to the students.
给同学们分
Divide it over.
分过去啊
This classroom
这间教室啊
It's the classroom that I attended before.
就是我之前旁听的教室
I'll just take this place as a classroom.
我干脆把这儿直接当课堂了
so much/many
这么多
Take them all.
都拿去
Read more books.
多看几本书
I have an envelope here.
我这儿有个信封
I come
我来
Let's divide it.
来 分一下
Before I came in, I wanted to borrow books.
我进来之前啊 本来是想借书的
There are two books on this list.
这书单上有两本书
Go and borrow it for me.
你去帮我借了吧
No problem. I'll borrow it for you later.
没问题 待会儿帮你借啊
Thank you
谢谢啊
Qunxian
群先
They won't bully you again, will they?
他们不会再欺负你们吧
brave
敢
Who dares to bully her
谁敢欺负她呀
If anyone bullies me
谁要是欺负我
I bite him.
我咬他
Mrs. Chen
陈师母
Your steamed stuffed bun is really delicious.
你这包子真是太好吃了
If I could eat it every day
我要是天天能吃到
Such a delicious steamed bun
这么好吃的包子
I'm even worth going to jail.
我坐监狱都值了
Silly child
傻孩子
Want to eat my bag for you every day
想吃我天天给你包
Thank you, Jenny.
谢谢师母
Eat more, class.
多吃点啊 同学们
Eat more, and you can pack it after eating.
都多吃点 吃完了还能包
Thank you, Jenny.
谢谢师母
It's delicious, Jenny
太好吃了师母
Yannian Qiaonian
延年 乔年
Keep your voice down. He's not awake yet.
小声点 他还没醒呢
Sir is still asleep.
先生还睡呢
right
对
good
好
wife of one's teacher/master
师母
十堰好
世炎好
Get me something to eat. I'm starving. I'm starving.
快给我拿点吃的 饿死我了都快
Get him two bags.
给他拿俩包包
hurry up
快快快
You know you came to see me.
你可算是知道来看我了
Look at you. I'm starving.
谁看你 我是饿扁了
Come and eat.
过来蹭口饭吃
My family is doing it now.
我现在家憋的
Don't know anything.
什么事都不知道
Tell me about it quickly
你赶紧给我说说
What's going on outside?
现在外面什么情况
I'm telling you, I'm always here.
我跟你说 我现在是寸步不离
Look, Mr. Shouchang can't go shopping.
看着守常先生不能上街
My news is full of
我这消息全是
My classmates who came back passed it on to me.
回来的同学给我传递的
Then stay in the red chamber.
那你在红楼待着
You're better informed than I am.
消息也比我灵通啊
Don't worry, eat slowly.
别着急 慢点吃
Let me tell you two pieces of bad news first.
我先给你们说两条坏消息
First, I this morning
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Tens of thousands of students in Beijing took to the streets to petition.
北京数万学生上街请愿
Fight against the military police
与军警展开斗争
Many students were injured.
很多学生受伤了
Hawick Lau; Lau Hoi Wai
刘海威
Liu Haiwei was also injured.
刘海威也受伤了
Luo Zhanglong
罗章龙
Which hospital?
哪家医院啊
It is said that there is no serious problem.
据说无大碍呀
But others saw him.
但别人看到他
It came when my head was bandaged.
头上包扎好了以后就来了
Decorate them with steamed stuffed buns.
你给他们再装点包子吧
It's estimated that when Shiyan leaves later.
估计一会儿世炎走的时候
Second, Beijing has now officially ordered
第二点 北京现在正式下令
Change the president of Peking University
更换北大校长
Cai Yuanpei was replaced by Hu Renyuan
由胡仁源替代蔡元培
Forget it. Forget it.
算了 不说这个了
There's still some good news.
还有几个好消息啊
this morning
今天上午
Military police only beat people, not arrest people.
军警只打人 不抓人了
Why?
为什么
Because there is no place to hold students.
因为已经没有地方关押学生了
This shows that the reactionaries are afraid.
这说明反动派害怕了
Second, today is not just a student.
第二 今天不光是学生
Workers, businessmen and citizens
工人 商人 市民
Petition on the streets.
全部上街请愿
The third point is the most important
第三点最最重要
Electricity was sent from Shanghai.
上海发来通电
The five major yarn mills of commercial press
商务印书馆 五大纱厂
All dock workers of Zhonghua Bookstore went on strike.
中华书局 码头工人全部罢工
All major shops in Nanjing Road went on strike.
南京路各大商店全部罢市
Even in front of the barber shop.
就连理发店门口也贴着
State affairs are so unintentional.
国事如此 无心整容
Please don't patronize the slogan.
请君不必光顾的标语
Do you know what this is called?
你们知道这叫什么吗
It's called three strikes.
这叫三罢
Students strike, workers strike, businessmen strike.
学生罢课 工人罢工 商人罢市
Mr. Dazhao said
大钊先生说了
As long as three strikes are formed.
只要形成了三罢
The nature of the student movement has changed.
学生运动的性质就发生了改变
Everyone is on their feet.
所有人都站起来了
All classes
所有各个阶级
All involved in patriotic action.
全部参与到爱国行动里面
Victory also knows the source code
胜利还会远吗
Great
太好了
But Mr. Dazhao said
但是大钊先生说
So as not to get excited and do something drastic.
以免他情绪激动 做出过激行为
I'm almost excited.
我都快激动了
You have locked me up.
你把我关起来得了
I'm just like you.
我跟你们一样
Zhong solved the death order.
仲澥下了死命令
Let me keep an eye on Mr. Shouchang.
让我一步不离看着守常先生
Don't say it's really dangerous.
还别说 真的非常危险
I saw it the day before yesterday.
前天我已经看到
Liu Yipin is already at Mr. Shouchang's tip in CHO.
刘一品已经在盯守常先生梢了
Liu yipin
刘一品
right
对
He and Zhang Fengzai are the same people.
他跟张丰载是一路人
Now, the police department
那现在警察厅
It's already Mr. Shouchang on the town.
已经町上守常先生了
So Zhong Jie won't let me leave.
所以仲澥不让我离开
Mr. Shouchang, half step
守常先生半步
Stop it, Deng Zhongxia. Now take my place.
别说了 邓中夏现在替我
Get some steamed buns out quickly.
赶紧拿点包子出来
Mr. Shouchang hasn't eaten yet
守常先生还没吃饭呢
Take some more.
再拿点儿
Take them all.
都拿过去吧
good
好
Jenny, I'm going first.
师母 我先走了
Be careful on the road. Okay
路上当心点啊 好
ok, thanks
好 谢谢
Be careful!
千万小心啊
good
好
sir
先生
The present situation is generally like this.
现在的情况大体是这样的
Many of our arrested students
我们很多被捕的学生
Locked up in the Third College of Literature and Law of Peking University.
被关在了北大的文 理 法三院
Now the citizens are going straight.
现在市民们直发地
Sent them water and food.
给他们送去了水 食物
And changing clothes.
还有换洗衣物
So I think
所以我觉得
Their mood should be relatively stable.
他们的情绪应该会比较稳定
But I don't think it will last long.
但是我觉得撑不了太久
I will organize with some classmates.
我会和几个同学一块儿去组织
visit their
看望他们
Let them not worry.
让他们千万不要着急
good
好
classmates
同学们
Now the struggle has reached a white-hot stage.
现在斗争已经到了白热化的阶段
The citizens have already got up.
市民们都已经起来了
I believe we just have to grind our teeth for a few more days.
我相信我们只要再咬牙坚持几天
The reactionaries will want to cooperate.
反动派就会要协
That turning point will appear.
那个转折点就会出现
but
但是
The more at this time.
越是在这个时候
The more we need to calm down.
我们大家越需要冷静
In case the reactionaries jump the wall.
以防反动派狗急跳墙
I see
明白了吧
Got it
明白了
good
好
What is the situation in the Third Hospital now?
现在三院是个什么情况
The third hospital is in good condition.
三院情况还好
But the second hospital is nervous.
但是二院那边比较紧张
That way.
那这样
Let some students
让一些同学
Go and touch the situation of the Second Hospital.
去摸一下二院的情况
At the same time, tell the students of the Second Hospital
同时告诉二院的同学们
Don't be impulsive.
一定不要冲动
Be calm and avoid the military police.
要冷静 要避开军警
At this time, in case of giving orders.
这个时候 以防授人以柄
Got it.
好知道了
wife of one's teacher/master
师母
sir
先生
Look who's here.
您看谁来了
wife of one's teacher/master
师母
Come in quickly.
您快进来
It's raining again
又下着雨
As soon as the road was asked, it came.
一路问着就走过来了
Look at the road and you're coming.
不远
good
好
Hello, Jenny.
师母 师母好
Hello, classmates.
同学们好
Sister!
姐啊
Didn't we discuss it at home?
咱俩人在家里头不是商量好了吗
Let you stay at home.
让你在家好好待着
It's so messy in the street outside now.
现在外头大街上那么乱
People are being arrested everywhere
到处都在抓人
You said you were calm.
你说你沉着个身子
What are you doing here?
你上这儿来干什么
I just heard that the school also arrested people.
我就是听说学校也抓人了
I don't trust
我不放心
Just came to see you.
就过来看看你
I brought you some food.
我给你们带了些吃的
And a change of clothes
还有换洗的衣服
You're still carrying something so heavy.
你还带着那么沉的东西
Sister!
姐呀
Don't say anything when all your classmates are here.
同学们都在 你就别说了
Students haven't eaten yet, have they
同学们都没吃饭呢吧
I came to bake you sesame cakes.
来 我给你们烙的烧饼
And the fire.
还有火烧
It's still hot.
还热乎着呢
Come on, everybody, come and eat.
来 大家快来吃
Thank you, madam. Thank you, madam.
谢谢师母 谢谢师母
Take it, take it, take it, take it
动手拿 动手拿 动手拿
Let me help you.
我帮您来
Try it all.
都尝尝
delicious
好吃
Taste it.
尝尝 尝尝
There's a fire here
这儿有火烧啊
Come and eat.
来 好吃吧
Delicious. Take some more
好吃
Would you like some pickles?
来点咸菜不
need not
不用
Then, sir, we'll go first.
那先生 我们先走了
Be sure to be safe.
一定注意安全
good
Okay.
Students must pay attention to safety.
同学们一定注意安全
nicely
好 好勒
If anyone is hungry, take some more.
谁要是饿了 再拿几个走
Yeah, no, no.
嗯 不用了 不用了
go
走
Be sure to be safe.
一定注意安全啊
nicely
好 好
We walked
我们走了
good
好
Sister Tang
汤吗 姐
Pour me a bowl.
帮我倒一碗
I'm really hungry.
不瞒你说 我还真是饿了
I just asked Shiyan to go to brother Zhongfu's house.
我刚才就让世炎去仲甫兄家
Get me something to eat.
帮我拿点吃的东西
He hasn't come back yet.
到现在也没回来
You really saved my life.
你真算是把我给救了
Give charcoal in the snow.
雪中送炭哪
give
给
It's the first time I've walked into school.
我还是第一次走进学校呢
The school is so beautiful.
学校好美啊
I remember when you were little.
我记得你小的时候
Carrying a schoolbag
背着书包
Bouncing to school
一蹦一跳地去学校
I'll watch you at the gate of the courtyard.
我就在院门口看着你
See nothing.
看到没影儿
I really admire you.
我真美慕你啊
Mei you can go to school.
美慕你能上学
I think the most beautiful voice in the world
我觉得天下最好听的声音
It's the loud and bright sound of school reading.
就是学校响亮亮的读书声
I also walked into the school today.
今天我也走进学校了
Look at these children.
你看这些孩子们
How energetic
多有精神啊
elder sister
姐
After dinner.
一会儿吃完饭
Let me show you around.
我带你去转转
what's up
怎么了
My stomach hurts.
肚子疼啊
no
没有 没有
No pain
不疼
Do you feel it?
你感受到了吗
He's kicking me
他在踢我呢
Kick me, too
也踢我呢
What are you kicking us for?
你踢我们干什么
You want to run out, too
你也想跑出来啊
I see
我知道
You also want to go to Peking University?
你也想上北大
Want dad to be your teacher?
想让爹爹当你的老师
yes or no
是不是
Dad is very strict.
爹爹可是很严厉的啊
When the time comes, if you cry.
到时候如果把你训哭了
Don't blame dad.
你可不许怪爹爹
elder sister
姐
Sorry
对不起啊
Look, I brought you to Beijing.
你看把你接到北京来
I should have stayed with you.
本来我应该好好陪着你
As a result, I was too busy to go home.
结果我忙得不着家
And in turn let you worry about me.
还反过来让你操心我
I'm sorry
对不起
I have hands and feet.
我有手有脚的
What do I want you to do with me?
我让你陪着我干什么
I am pregnant.
我是怀孕了
Not sick again.
又不是生病了
I can manage myself.
我能管好我自己
Don't worry about it.
不用你操心
Look at yourself.
你倒看看你自己吧
I haven't seen you for a few days
几天不见
Just lost a lap.
就瘦了一圈
I don't know you yet.
我还不知道你
Get busy together
一忙起来
A cold bite and a hot bite.
一口冷的 一口热的
Just messing around there.
就在那儿瞎对付
We can't do this anymore.
以后可不能这样了啊
I brought you a change of clothes.
我给你带了点儿换洗的衣服
Are these two enough?
就这两件够吗
Enough is enough?
够了吧
I'm also taking two children.
我也是带着俩孩子
Can't get away.
走不开
It's a pity that your wife will help me today.
亏得今天树贵媳妇儿来帮我
Otherwise, I won't be able to visit you.
要不然我还来看不了你呢
So, sister
那这样 姐
Let's discuss it again.
咱俩再商量商量
I promise you.
我答应你
From now on, I will have a good meal.
从此以后我好好吃饭
But you have to promise me.
但是你也得答应我
You can't go out again.
你不能再往外跑了
You said it was so messy outside now.
你说现在外边那么乱
I'm by your side.
我不在你身边
I can't take care of you.
我又没法照顾你
I already owe you a lot.
我已经对你亏欠很多了
Han Tuo, you know what?
憨坨 你知道吗
Baohua can be yours now.
葆华现在可随你了
I read there in the morning every morning.
这每天一大早就在那儿晨读
He can't recite poems.
他背不下来诗啊
Don't even eat.
连饭都不吃
It's like when you were little.
这多像你小的时候啊
You were like this when you were a kid.
你小的时候就这样
Can't recite the article
背不出文章来
You hide in that chicken coop and cry.
你就躲到那鸡窝里去哭
I'm afraid to hear
怕我听到
With his mouth still humming and swallowing.
还捂着嘴鸣鸣咽咽的
I'm telling you.
我还说呢
Where did you get a wild cat?
这哪儿来的一只野猫啊
elder sister
姐
You sleep at night
你晚上睡觉啊
Still studying there.
还在那儿苦读
That candle burned your hair.
那蜡烛把你头发都给燎了
You don't even know
你都不知道
Almost burned down our house.
差点把咱房子都给烧了
elder sister
姐
You forgot all about it.
你都忘了
I want to talk to you about my heart.
我想跟你说说我的心里话
I think I've been Li Dazhao all my life.
我觉得我李大钊这辈子
I am worthy of the world.
我对得起天下
I am worthy of my teacher.
我对得起我的师长
Be worthy of my friend.
对得起我的朋友
I'm worthy of my students.
我也对得起我那帮学生
But I'm sorry for you.
但是我对不起你
Ever since you followed me
你自打跟了我以后
Always worried about me.
一直为我提心吊胆的
Always worrying about me.
一直为我操心
I feel sorry for you.
我觉得我对不起你
Shouchang
守常
You are a man of great importance.
你是于大事的人
Every time you tell me the big things
你每次跟我讲的那些大事儿
I can understand some of them.
我有的听得懂
Some don't understand.
有的听不懂
but
但是
I don't care if I understand it or not.
我不管我懂不懂啊
I knew it.
我就知道啊
You are working for others.
你是在为别人做事
Work for the common people
为老百姓做事
It's a good thing to do.
做的是大好事
So I can't hold you back.
所以我不能拖你后腿
I will keep my home for you.
我会把家给你守好的
You can rest assured.
你就放心吧
I think so.
我想好了
I'll take the baby with me one of these days.
过些日子 我就带着孩子
Dahuituo
回大黑坨
Give birth there.
在那儿生孩子
Don't distract you
不让你分心
So you don't have to worry about us.
省得你老记挂着我们
it suddenly occurs to me that
对了
It's this
这个是
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
From your new water
从你的薪水里
The deducted money
扣出来的钱
I've been saving it for you
我一直给你存着呢
I took out all my household items.
我把家用都拿出来了
There are so many left.
还剩下这么多
I know you are useful.
我知道你有用
Here you go.
你拿去吧
Hantuo
憨坨
You know my happiest thing.
你知道我最开心的事
What is it?
是什么吗
I'm happiest.
我最开心的就是
Copy that. You're from Tianjin
收到你从天津
A letter sent to me from Japan
从日本给我寄过来的信
I'll just take those letters.
我就拿着那些信哪
Just go to a door tree.
就到咱门村
Let Mr. Big read it to me
让大先生给我读
After reading it.
读完了以后
I am under the kerosene lamp at night.
晚上我就在煤油灯下
I just watch it over and over again.
我就一遍一遍地看
I painted it with my hand.
我就用手描画着
Those words you wrote.
你写的那些字
I was just thinking.
我就在想
I wish I could read.
我要是认字就好了
If I can read
我要是认字
I can give it to my silly lump
我就能给我的憨坨
Write a letter
写封信
I can talk to my idiot.
我就能跟我的憨坨
Tell me what's on my mind.
说说我的心里话
Don't look
不许看
Turn your face away.
把脸转过去
What word?
什么字
plum
李
this
这个
big
大
What about this?
这个呢
I can't recognize this word.
这仨字我还能不认识
elder sister
姐
I promise you.
我跟你保证
Wait till one day.
等有朝一日
The school can put one.
学校可以摆上一张
When the desk is quiet
安静课桌的时候
When you can hear the sound of reading aloud.
可以传出朗朗的读书声的时候
I take you with me.
我带着你
Just the two of us.
就咱们俩人
In a classroom.
在一个教室里头
Sunlight comes in from the outside.
阳光从外头透进来
I'll do it.
我一笔
Yihua
一画
at one stroke
一笔
Teach you to write by drawing.
一画地教你写字
Then I sat down at the bottom.
然后我坐在底下
I'll be waiting for you.
我等着你
What are you waiting for?
等着你什么呢
You write a letter to me yourself.
你亲手写一封信给我
Where do I want to see?
我要看哪
I promise you.
我跟你保证
Eat quickly.
快吃吧
eat rice
吃饭
[Zhao Renlan, wife of Li Dazhao, died 28 May 1933, aged 49. In June 1936, the CPC Hebei Provincial Committee posthumously recognized her as a member of the Communist Party of China.]
[赵纫兰，李大钊夫人。1933年5月28日病逝，享年49岁。1936年6月，中共河北省委追认她为中国共产党党员。]
What are you going to do?
您干什么去
Go around
出去转转
impossible
不行
Zhongfu can't
仲甫 不行啊
I finished writing my manuscript.
我稿子写完了
I'll go out and have a look.
我 我出去看看
Didn't you promise Shouchang not to go out?
你不是答应守常不出门吗
I finished writing my manuscript.
我稿子写完了
I'm going out to have a look.
我要出去看看
Yes, I konw.
我知道啊
Whether Shouchang asked me to stay at home
无论是守常让我在家里
Make up "New Youth"
编《新青年》也好
Or Yannian doesn't go out and look at me.
还是延年不出去看着我也好
impossible
不行
It's all for my own safety. I know
都是为了我的安全着想 我知道
I didn't want to cause you any trouble.
我呢一来不想给你们添麻烦
Second, come on
二来呢
I really want to calm down at home.
我也确实想在家静下心来
Write the manuscript of this issue well.
好好地把这一期的稿子写好
Sir, you can't go out.
先生 您不能出去
I need and I have to know.
我需要 而且我必须要知道
Present
当下的
impossible
不行
development of the situation
形势发展
What I really want
我要真想干的事
Can you stop it?
你们拦得住吗
Hurry and steam steamed buns.
赶紧蒸包子吧
I have to send it to them.
还得给他们送过去呢
Severely punish traitors
严惩卖国贼
Refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
拒签巴黎和约
Ah, come on, go
快点啊 快走
Be honest.
老实点儿
Refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
拒签巴黎和约
Severely punish traitors
严惩卖国贼
Duihuajie Duihua
郎对花姐对花
A pair went to Tian Xia.
一对对到田埂下
Drop a seed and send a bud.
丢下一粒籽 发了一颗芽
What flowers bloom in the leaves of the pole?
么杆子么叶 开的什么花
This country
此次归国
I want to start a magazine.
我是想创办一份杂志
As a way to awaken the political consciousness of Chinese people
作为唤醒国人政治的觉悟的
And the clarion call of ethical consciousness.
和伦理的觉悟的号角
I assure you.
我向各位保证
Let me run a magazine for ten years
让我办十年杂志
The whole country's thoughts will change for it.
全国思想都会为之改观
Guowei
国家濒危
But the authorities fought the rabbit with the lion's strength.
当局却以狮子搏兔之力
Play against our patriotism.
弹压我等爱国之心
It makes me feel that in my own country.
让我感觉到在自己的国家
Be bullied as much as Japan.
和在日本一样地受欺负
What hope is there for such a country
这样的国家还有什么希望
Two gentlemen
二位先生
You have to save this country.
你们要救救这个国家
Save this nation.
救救这个民族
A man like us
像我们这样一个
Most of them are farmers and illiterate countries.
大多数都是农民和文盲的国家
How can we make it work?
到底怎么样才能走得通
The Road of Intersecting Science with Democracy
科学和民主相交轨的路
What flowers bloom in the leaves of the pole?
么杆子么叶 开的什么花
There is no light in the liberal arts room.
文科学长室没亮灯啊
Then where will he go?
那他会去哪儿呢
Take a look at the playground.
走操场看看去
陈中富
陈仲甫
Zhongfu
仲甫
中富兄
仲甫兄
Are you there
在吗
not have
没有
I said watch him, watch him.
我就说看好他看好他
With his character
以他这个性格
Seeing such a situation now
看见现在这么 一个形势
Something will happen to him.
他肯定会出事啊
中富兄
仲甫兄
陈中富
陈仲甫
Look for it
找 找 找
Where to go, Shouchang
走哪儿啊 守常
Looking for
找啊
Where are you going to look?
你去哪儿找啊
We looked for the first hospital, the second hospital and the third hospital.
一院二院 三院我们都找了
Mashenmiao north riverside honglou playground
马神庙 北河沿 红楼操场
He is not here.
他都不在
Jun's sister-in-law is also looking for him.
君曼嫂子也都在找他
Let's not worry now.
我们现在别着急
Let's think about where he will go.
我们想想他会去哪儿
All I can think about is home and school.
我想到的只有家 还有学校
Bian Junman's sister-in-law is waiting for him at home.
家里边 君曼嫂子等着他
The two of us will wait here.
学校 我们俩在这儿等
Shizhi asked you a question.
适之 问你一个问题
This is still us.
这还是我们
Is it worth fighting for?
值得为之奋斗的民国吗
Or these martyrs in Qiu Jin, Xu Xilin?
这还是徐锡麟 秋瑾这些烈士
A Republic in exchange for blood?
抛头颅 洒热血换来的共和吗
This classroom
这间教室
We could have set a clean desk.
我们本可以摆上一张干净的课桌
Let the students be quiet inside.
让学生们在里头安安静静地
To enjoy the pleasure of knowledge.
去享受知识的乐趣
But now it's a prison.
可是现在呢 变成了监狱
Look at my students inside.
里边关着我的学生
Lock up your students.
关着你的学生
Look at brother Guan Zhongfu's students
关着仲甫兄的学生
What's scary is the doorway.
可怕的是门口
There are still a group of parents in pain.
竟然还有一群痛苦不堪的父母
With their pleading eyes.
他们用祈求的眼神
Seeking help from others.
在寻求别人帮助
Even kneeling down to the military police.
甚至在向军警下跪
What's even more ridiculous is that
更荒谬的是
They are patriotic for their children.
他们是为了自己的孩子爱国
And kneel down to the military police
而向军警下跪啊
What's wrong with this country
这个国家怎么了
Don't you think this country is ridiculous?
你没觉得这个国家很荒唐吗
Shouchang, don't blame yourself
守常 你不要自责
This is not your responsibility alone.
这不是你一个人的责任
We really can't go on foolhardy.
我们真的不能蛮干下去了
Now each and every one of us
我们现在每一个人
You have to think about it.
都要好好想一想
Review one's thinking
检讨一下自己的思路
Otherwise, only students will be humiliated.
否则 受辱的只有学生
Only the school was damaged.
受损的只有学校
It's like I was
就像是我在
It's the same as written in "Beijing Students' Disgraces"
《北京学生受辱记》里写的一样
Shizhi, are we at fault?
适之 我们有错吗
Are students at fault?
学生们有错吗
You say such things at this time.
你这个时候你说这种话
Aren't you opening your eyes for the reactionary government?
你不是在为反动政府张目吗
At this time
这个时候
Don't put a hat on me, Shouchang
你就别给我戴帽子了 守常
You mentioned your students just now.
刚才你提到你的学生
Yes, we all saw it.
是我们都看到了
You feel bad and I feel bad.
你难受 我也难受
But what can I do?
可是有什么办法呢
If we hadn't had a general strike.
如果当初我们不实行总罢课
If we adopt some mitigating measures
如果我们采用一些缓和的办法
Our Peking University won't
我们北大不至于
Come to this point.
走到现在这个地步
Shizhi, why do we want to strike?
适之 我们为什么要罢课呀
Why are we striking?
我们为什么罢课呀
It's not because the government wants to sign that.
不是因为政府要签订那个
The Paris Peace Treaty that humiliated the country?
丧权辱国的巴黎和约吗
We don't do it again and again.
我们不是一而再再而三地
To protest against the invalid appeal.
去抗议 申诉无效
Do you have to do it?
不得已而为之的吗
Is patriotism guilty?
难道爱国有罪吗
Traitorous deeds!
卖国有功啊
Patriotism has many ways.
爱国它有很多途径
There are many ways and means to save the country.
救国有很多的方式和方法
还有寿昌
还有 守常
I heard that you recently
我听说你最近
Has been advocating the Russian revolution
一直在鼓吹俄国革命
Say we Chinese.
说我们中国人
We must take the Russian road.
必须走俄国人的道路
It's dangerous.
这很危险
What's the danger?
有什么危险的呢
I advise you not to always dictate the American way.
我劝你也不要总町着美国人的路
Don't always believe in Dewey's experimentalism
不要总信奉杜威的那个实验主义
You should be as compatible as Mr Cai said.
你应该像蔡先生说的那样 兼容
You have to have a look.
你要看一看
The situation and changes after the Great War
大战之后的形势和变化
You're going too far again.
你又扯远了
We're talking about the present.
现在我们谈的是眼下
How do we save Peking University
我们如何救北大
How do we save those of us
我们如何解救我们那些
Arrested students
被捕的学生
We have to do something. We have to do something.
我们要想办法呀 要想办法
It's no use worrying.
着急没用的
Let's be quiet, quiet can make us wise.
我们要安静 静能生慧
think of a way
想办法
My opinion is that we should cancel the strike.
我的意见是 我们要取消罢课
We have to give the government a step down.
我们要给政府一个台阶下
Never cancel the strike.
绝不能取消罢课
The strike must not be cancelled at this time.
这个时候绝不能取消罢课
We don't have a second way now.
我们现在没有第二条路
There is only one way for us.
我们只有一条路
That is to adopt a more determined way.
那就是采用更加坚决的方式
Let's fight.
我们去斗争
struggle
斗争
Do you still have to fight?
你还要斗争吗
What's the use of struggle
斗争有什么用
Now you and Chen Zhongfu are covered in scars.
现在你和陈仲甫满身都是伤疤了
Do you still have to fight and go to extremes?
你还要斗争 还要走极端吗
Chen Zhongfu, he is the leader of our new culture.
陈仲甫他是我们新文化的领袖
Three of us.
我们三个人
Why can't we just do a new culture?
为什么不能只做好新文化
Why are we going?
我们为什么要往
Wang is treading in this muddy water.
这汪浑水里边蹚呢
Go on like this.
再这样下去
Not only is Peking University finished.
不仅是北大完了
And you two.
还有你们俩
You two will ruin your academic career.
你们俩会毁了你们的学术前程
You will ruin your happy family.
你们会毁了你们的幸福家庭
Shizhi, ah
适之啊
Let's advocate the new culture movement.
咱们去倡导新文化运动
Is to inspire people's wisdom.
是为了启发民智
So what happens when the people wake up?
那么国民觉悟了之后呢
There's bound to be some action.
势必会有所行动
All thoughts have no actions.
光有思想 没有行动
Can't save the country.
是救不了国家的
I'm not talking about us
我不是说我们
Don't act at all
完全不去行动
I mean, you must stop going to extremes.
我是说你们一定不能再走极端
There should be an objective standard for not being extreme.
极不极端应该有一个客观的标准
If a country's power trumps justice
如果一个国家强权压倒了公理
If a country
如果一个国家
Involving the core interests.
涉及到核心利益
When the will of the people cannot be expressed.
而人民的意愿不能表达的时候
So the citizens of this country
那么这个国家的公民
You can exercise your democratic rights.
就可以行使民主的权利
Let's take Japan as an example
我们拿日本举一个例子
China was defeated in Sino-Japanese War of 1894-1895
中日甲午战争 中国战败了
We cede land for compensation.
我们割地 赔款
Even gave Taiwan Province to the Japanese.
甚至把台湾都让给日本人了
We can't help it. We have no temper.
没办法 我们没脾气
But now we are the victorious country, Shizhi.
可现在我们是战胜国呀 适之
Why does Germany take our Qingdao?
凭什么德国把我们的青岛
Give it to Japan?
让给日本呢
Is there any axiom in this?
这还有公理吗
If we let those traitors go.
如果我们放任那些卖国贼
If you trample on public opinion wantonly
肆意妄为践踏民意的话
What about our country?
那我们这个国家
Can it still be called a democratic republic?
还能叫一个民主共和国吗
Do we deserve to be called citizens of our country?
我们还配叫国家的公民吗
So for the national interest
所以为了国家利益
Now we need a complete revolution.
我们现在需要一个彻底的革命
Combine ideological awareness with action awareness.
把思想觉悟和行动觉悟结合起来
I, Li Dazhao, would like to be this Depth Charge.
我李大钊愿意当这个急先锋
Nine without regret.
九死而不悔
Although thousands of people have gone.
虽千万人吾往矣
Zhongfu, where have you been?
仲甫 你去哪儿了
I'm fine
我没事
I sat there for a while.
我在那儿坐了一会儿
My, uh.
我那个
I went for a spin.
我去转了一圈
寿昌说得对
守常说得对
Let me stay at home and not let me go.
让我在家待看 不让我去
I'm going home.
我这就回家
It's over. I'm
完了我 我
I'm hungry.
我饿了
I want to go home for dinner.
我要回家吃饭
I'm thirsty, too.
我也渴了 嘴干
it doesn't matter
没事
I'm fine
我没事
Zhongfu
仲甫
陈中富
陈仲甫
The Republic is dead.
共和死了
I will not die
我不会死
Mom!
妈妈 妈妈
When will dad come back?
爸爸什么时候回来
I'm hungry
我都饿了
Wait a minute.
再等会儿
We didn't eat well until Dad came back.
爸爸回来我们才吃得香
Come back
回来了
Why don't you eat?
你们怎么不吃饭
How can we eat if you don't come back?
你不回来 我们怎么吃呀
Yannian and Qiaonian didn't eat at noon.
延年和乔年中午都没吃饭呢
Waiting for you.
都等你呢
Come on, sit down
快 来吧 坐下
I made a hot pot
我弄了个火锅
Improve for everyone.
给大家改善改善
Come sit down.
来 坐下
Sit down, sit down.
坐吧 坐下
Junman
君曼
I want to say sorry to you.
我要跟你说声对不起
because
因为
I am not a qualified husband.
我不是一个合格的丈夫
Yannian
延年
Qiaonian
乔年
Henian
鹤年
Zimei
子美
And zilan.
还有白兰
There are Yuying and Songnian in their hometown.
还有远在老家的玉莹和松年
I want to say sorry to you, too.
我都要对你们也说声对不起
Because I am not a qualified father.
因为我不是一个合格的父亲
It is better to come back than anything else.
人回来比什么都强
Don't say sorry.
别说对不起了
Just hear me out.
你听我说完
I stayed at home for three days.
我在家里憋了三天
I went out for a roll today.
今天出去转了一圈
As you can imagine.
你们应该能够想象到
What I see
我看到了什么
I was a young man.
我是一个年轻时候
A revolutionary who is determined to save the country.
就立志救国的革命者
But I am not a good teacher.
但我不是一个好的老师
Because I look at those students
因为我看着那些学生
Be trapped in the picture circle because of loving the country.
因为爱国家而身陷囹圄
So I have to take this step.
所以 我必须要走出这一步
Your father
你们的父亲
You have to kill yourself before you die.
必须要先让自己置之死地而后生
Our children's family has just passed.
孩子们我们家刚刚过上了
A few years of stability
几年安定的日子
But in the future
可是今后
You may face different situations again.
可能你们又将要面临不同的处境
Because I can't keep my eyes shut.
因为我不能眼睁睁地
Watching my students bleed and cry.
看着我的学生们流血 流泪
Be unmoved by
而无动于衷
I have to fight with them.
我必须要跟他们在一起去战斗
Because I love this country.
因为我爱这个国家
This country is not only mine.
这个国家不仅是我的
It's even yours.
更是你们的
I want to do something for this country.
我要为这个国家去做点什么
from now on
今后
Maybe because of me.
可能因为我
You will also suffer.
你们还会受连累
Maybe because of me in the future
今后 可能因为我
You will also suffer hardships.
你们还会吃苦受罪
so
所以
I have to say sorry to you.
我必须要跟你们说对不起
This glass of wine is to make amends to you.
这杯酒是向你们赔罪的
Are you okay?
没事吧
Although I'm six, I can't drink.
虽然我有六不许 不能饮酒
But today, I also want to propose a toast to apology.
但是今天我也要敬赔罪酒
Because I am also determined to devote myself to my country.
因为我也是立志要为国家献身的
As the eldest son
作为长子
I may not be filial to my parents.
我可能不能为父母尽孝
Can't do one's duty for younger brothers and sisters.
不能为弟弟妹妹尽责
Today, I'll apologize with this glass of wine.
今天我就以这杯酒谢罪了
me too
我也是
I'll drink this wine myself.
这杯酒 我自己喝
alright
好了 好了
Let's not say anything unlucky.
咱们都不说不吉利的话了
Come on, everybody, sit down and eat.
来 大家赶紧坐下吃饭
we
咱们
Our family must live well.
咱们一家人一定要好好地活着
Sit down, sit down.
坐下来坐下
dad
爸
I'll fill it up for you
我给您斟满
eat rice
吃饭